Matthew Rees

Applied Ecologist

Curriculum Vitae

August 2020

♀ School of Biosciences, University of Melbourne

matthewreesearch.com

+61 412 560 534

matt.wayne.rees@gmail.com

@matt_w_rees

matt-w-rees

in matthew-w-rees

About me

I conduct research on predator ecology, invasive animal management and native mammal conservation. To do so, I use quantitative methods which incorporate uncertainty and socio-economic constraints to improve management and decision-making. In particular, my strengths lie in statistical models which estimate animal density, occupancy, spatio-temporal interactions and the integration of different data sources. I'm also passionate about collaborative, open science that incorporates the knowledge and needs of First Nations people. I am currently finishing up my PhD with the QAECO lab on the impact of fox control in south-west Victoria, while tackling the occasional, related contracting job.

Education

2017-present PhD (Conservation Biology) University of Melbourne

Melbourne, Australia

2013-2016 Bachelor of Environmental Science (1st class Honours) Queensland University of Technology

Brisbane, Australia

Professional Experience

2020–2020 Research assistant, University of Melbourne, Designing fox density surveys for DELWP knowledge acquisition grant.

2019–2020 **Ecologist**, Winda-mara Aboriginal Corporation, training Indigenous rangers in fauna monitoring protocols.

2018–2020 **Demonstrator**, University of Melbourne, Conservation Biology, Environmental Risk Assessment subjects.

Publications

Peer-reviewed

- 1. Rees, M, J Pascoe, B Wintle, M Le Pla, E Birnbaum, and B Hradsky (2019). Unexpectedly high densities of feral cats in a rugged temperate forest. *Biological Conservation*.
- 2. Rees, M, J Carwardine, A Reeson, and J Firn (2020). Rapidly assessing cobenefits to advance threat-management alliances. *Conservation Biology*.

In peer-review

1. Davies, H, Tiwi Land Rangers, M Rees, D Stokeld, A Miller, G Gillespie, B Murphy. Variation in feral cat density between two large adjacent islands in Australia's monsoon tropics. *Biological Invasions*.

Reports

1. Rees, M (2020). Monitoring and managing critical weight range mammals in the indigenous protected areas of the world heritage Budj Bim cultural landscape. A report prepared for the Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning.

Awards

2017	Australian government RTP PhD scholarship	\$98K
2017	DELWP PhD top-up scholarship	\$15K
2016	CSIRO honours top-up scholarship	\$10K
2015	University of Wollongong undergraduate research scholarship	\$7.2K

Grants

2020	Hoslworth research endowment	\$7.5K
2019	Hoslworth research endowment	\$6.75K
2018	Conservation Ecology Centre student scholarship	\$5K
2017	Victorian Environmental Assesment Council Bill Borthwick scholarship	\$2K
2017	Parks Victoria research partners program	\$20K
2017	DELWP research grant	\$15K

Presentations

- ➤ International Statistical Ecology Conference (virtual), June 2020. Using spatial mark-resight and GAMs to infer predator interactions.
- ➤ Guest lecture, University of Melbourne, Australian Wildlife Biology subject, May 2020, *Invasive mammals in Australia*.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Launceston, November 2019, Does fox control increase feral cat population density?
- ➤ Wimmera Biodiversity Seminar, Rupanyup, September 2019, Interactions between invasive predators and threatened native mammals in south-west VIC.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2019, Interactions between invasive predators and threatened native mammals in the Otway Ranges.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2019, Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin to benefit both threatened species and agriculture.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Brisbane, November 2018, Modelling invasive predator density in mesic forests.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2018, How many feral cats are there in the Western Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Mathematics of Biological Systems Symposium, Melbourne, April 2018, *Integrating co-benefits into the cost-effective prioritisation of conservation strategies*.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2018, How many feral cats are there in the Western Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Environmental Institute of Australia & New Zealand conference, Brisbane, August 2017, Building alliances between the agriculture and conservation sectors.

Media

09/12/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Invasive predators interactions
08/08/2019	Radio interview	3AW	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
08/08/2019	Newspaper article (front page)	Geelong Advertiser	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
07/08/2019	Radio interview	ABC South West Victoria	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
13/03/2019	Newspaper article	Colac Herald	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	TV interview	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Online news article	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Ballarat	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges

Service

- ➤ Treasurer, Biosciences Postgraduate Society (2019-2020).
- ➤ Peer-reviewer, Wildlife Research and Conservation Biology journals.
- ➤ Award judging panel member, Ecological Society of Australia (2020).
- > Social media manager, QAECO lab.

Referees

- ➤ Dr Bronwyn Hradsky, PhD supervisor, bronwyn.hradsky@unimelb.edu.au
- ➤ Prof. Brendan Wintle, PhD supervisor, b.wintle@unimelb.edu.au
- ➤ Dr Alan Robley, PhD supervisor, alan.robley@delwp.vic.gov.au
- ➤ Dr Jack Pascoe, Collaborator, jack@conservationecologycentre.org